你要去哪里
Where are you going?
切尔诺贝利
Chernobyl.
前情提要
伊格纳滕科  消防和救援站的  我得找到他
Ignatenko, fire and rescue unit. I need to find him!
莫斯科  第六医院
Moscow. Hospital number six.
你是为火灾来的吗
Are you here because of the fire?
有什么我们需要担心的吗
Anything we should be worried about?
没有
No.
他们不能飞到堆芯上方
It cannot go over the core.
瑞典的一座核电站检测到了辐射
The nuclear plant in Sweden has detected radiation.
至少疏散普里皮亚季
At least evacuate Pripyat.
当熔岩进入这些水箱
When the lava enters these tanks,
水会立即过热并蒸发
it will instantly superheat,
这会引起严重的热爆炸
causing a significant thermal explosion.
我们还有多少时间
And how long before this happens?
大约48到72小时
Approximately 48 to 72 hours,
但是我们也许有办法
but we may have a solution.
切尔诺贝利
第三集
原创翻译  双语字幕
最新连载海外影视剧下载
请登陆 www.YYeTs.com
仅供交流学习  禁止商用盈利
翻译     草草  Eunice  elingbow  哈里不是波特
翻译     水龙吟  tong大梨  Sakura小书包
翻译     小胖橘子  DerbyNinja  伊森泽生  小酸奶
顾问     elingbow
校对     草草  苏葵
时间轴     荞麦麦  Caroline
后期     拉图
总监     苏葵
他们会不会已经被水辐射死了
Is it possible that the water has already killed them?
有可能
Yes.
那怎么办
Then what?
如果这办法不行的话
If it doesn't work?
送他们上车
Get them in the truck.
把软管接过来  开始泵水
Get the hoses in! Start pumping!
莫斯科第六医院
1986年4月30日
爆炸发生四天后
我是来见我丈夫的  瓦西里·伊格纳滕科
Uh, I'm here to see my husband, Vasily Ignatenko.
他是切尔诺贝利的消防员  我有准许的
He's a firefighter from Chernobyl. I have permission.
切尔诺贝利  抱歉  不得探视
Chernobyl? I'm sorry, no visitors.
布洛夫少校说
Well, but Major Burov told me,
-他说  -无人例外
- he said-- - No exceptions.
求你了  我从基辅州远道而来
Please. I've come all the way from Kievskaya Oblast.
不好意思
Excuse me.
打扰一下
Excuse me, excuse me.
你是谁  你来这里干什么
Who are you? What are you doing here?
-我有通行证  -你不能进来  不安全
- I have a pass. - You can't be here. It's not safe.
我是来见我丈夫的
I am here to see my husband.
瓦西里·伊格纳滕科
Vasily Ignatenko.
他是切尔诺贝利的消防员
He's a firefighter from Chernobyl.
我知道伊格纳滕科是谁  但你不能见他
I know who Ignatenko is, but you can't.
我有准许的
I have permission. I-I've...
你可以探视30分钟  多一分钟都不行
You can see him for 30 minutes, not a minute more.
你绝不能碰他  明白吗
And you cannot touch him in any way. Do you understand?
-好  -15号房
- Yeah. - Room 15.
谢谢
Thank you.
-你没怀孕吧  -没有
- You're not pregnant, are you? - No.
那个我不用给你
I won't have to give that to you.
在这儿呢
There they are.
不  等等  我还没打完呢
No, wait, wait, wait. I haven't finished yet.
是啊
No, he hasn't.
嗯  可以了
Yeah, that's good.
好点了
Yeah, better.
看看是谁来了
Look who the cat dragged in.
我怎么说的
What did I tell you?
我就是躲不开你  是吧
There's no hiding from you, is there?
轻点  轻点  没事的
Easy, easy. It's okay.
我们没事  没事的
We're all okay. Yeah, we're okay.
怎么会这样的  是谁让他们这么做的
How, how, how did this happen? Who gave them the idea?
-你是说是我吗  -反正是有人
- Are you suggesting I did? - Someone did.
有人决定了把疏散区
Someone decided that the evacuation zone
划为30公里半径  而我们知道  这里
should be 30 kilometers, when we know, here,
高美尔区探测到了铯137
Cesium-137 in the Gomel district.
-那都是200公里外了  -反正就是决定了
- That's 200 kilometers away! - It was decided.
-理由呢  -我不知道
- Based on what? - I don't know!
请原谅  或许我是在实验室里待久了
Forgive me. Maybe I've just spent too much time in my lab.
或是我愚蠢
Or maybe I'm just stupid.
事情就这么办的吗
Is this really the way it all works?
某个共产党官员
An uninformed, arbitrary decision
职业党员做出的无知
that will cost who knows how many lives
武断的决定  将害死天知道多少人
made by some apparatchik, some career party man?
我就是职业党员
I'm a career party man.
你说话该小心点  列加索夫同志
You should watch your tone, Comrade Legasov.
同志们
Comrades...
我们亲眼证实火几乎被扑灭了
We have visual confirmation that the fire is nearly extinguished.
碘131和铯137的排放量
There has also been a reduction in iodine 131
也有所减少
and cesium-137 emissions.
这是好事  对吧
Good. Yes?
但温度在上升
But the temperature is rising.
还有
And, uh...
锆95排放量激增
There's a spike in zirconium-95.
来自于燃料棒包覆层上的锆95
It's from the cladding on the fuel rods.
什么意思
Meaning what?
说明熔毁已经开始了
The meltdown has begun.
把它拿开
Get it off me!
别动了
Stop moving!
放开他  你弄疼他了
Get off him! You're hurting him!
-你不能进来  -他怎么了
- You can't be in here. - What's happening to him?
快出去
Get out!
你不能进来
You can't be in here!
1986年5月2日
莫斯科请求"帮帮我们"
熔毁可能在十年内导致一万人死亡
-喂  -谢比纳同志来电
- Yes? - Comrade Shcherbina is on the phone.
转接进来
Put him through.
怎么样
Well?
火快被扑灭了
The fire's nearly out.
起泡箱里的水正被抽出
The bubbler tanks are being drained.
我们已经成功消除了热爆炸的风险
We have successfully eliminated the risk of a thermal explosion.
还有呢
And?
但堆芯内部的
The situation inside the core
熔毁速度比预期更快
is deteriorating faster than anticipated.
混凝土层能撑六到八周
The concrete pad will last for six to eight weeks,
但之后  列加索夫预测有50%的机会
but after that, Legasov estimates a 50% chance
燃料会熔穿混凝土层
that the fuel will breach the pad
流入地下水
and melt down into the groundwater itself.
这些地下水流往哪里
And where does this groundwater go?
普里皮亚季河
The Pripyat River,
最终流入第聂伯河
which feeds into the Dnieper.
那是约五千万人口的主要供水系统
The primary water supply for approximately 50 million people,
更不用说庄稼和牲畜
not to mention crops and livestock,
此水源将...不能使用
would be... unusable.
我们建议在混凝土层下安装热交换器
We're recommending we install a heat exchanger under the pad
以降低堆芯温度  暂停熔毁
to lower the core temperature and halt the meltdown.
要这么做  据说我们需要
And in order to do that, I'm told that we will need...
全苏联所有的液氮
all of the liquid nitrogen in the Soviet Union.
-好吧  -当然了  我们还需要...
- All right. - Yeah, and of course, we'll also need--
你需要什么都给你
Whatever you need, you have it.
-你现在应该明白了  -是的
- That should be clear by now. - Yes.
-还有事吗  -没有了  谢谢您
- Anything else? - No, no, no. Thank you.
还有  我想说一下30公里半径的禁区
Yes. I'd like to address the 30-kilometer exclusion zone.
等等  什么  列加索夫教授  是你吗
Wait, what? Professor Legasov, is that you?
什么禁区
What exclusion zone?
只是无关紧要的细节  总书记
Minor details, General Secretary.
部长会议主席雷日科夫已经决定...
Um, Premier Ryzhkov has determined that--
如果他决定了  那就是决定了
If he determined, then he determined.
听着  列加索夫教授
Look, Professor Legasov,
你去那里只有一个原因
you are there for one reason only.
明白吗  就是制止这一切
Do you understand? To make this stop.
我不想听问题
I don't want questions.
我想知道什么时候结束
I want to know when this will be over.
如果你是问切尔诺贝利什么时候彻底安全
If you mean when will Chernobyl be completely safe,
钚239的半衰期是两万四千年
the half-life of plutonium-239 is 24,000 years.
所以应该说"这辈子都不会安全"
So perhaps we should just say, "Not within our lifetimes."
咱们俩应该出去走走
I think you and I should take a walk.
太晚了  我累了
It's late. I'm tired.
我们要去走走
We're taking a walk.
你想听什么  要我道歉吗
Was it you want? An apology?
我不会袖手旁观...
Not gonna sit back and...
我们的小伙子们会发生什么
What will happen to our boys?
哪些小伙子  潜水员吗
Which boys? The divers?
潜水员  消防员  控制室的操作员
The divers, the firefighters, the men in the control room.
辐射具体会对他们造成什么影响
What does the radiation do to them precisely?
就其中有些人接受的辐照水平而言
At the levels some of them were exposed?
电离辐射会破坏细胞结构
Ionizing radiation tears the cellular structure apart.
皮肤会起水泡  变红  然后变黑
The skin blisters, turns red, then black.
之后会有一段潜伏期
This is followed by a latency period.
即时效应会缓和下来
The immediate effects subside.
患者似乎开始恢复
The patient appears to be recovering.
甚至显得很健康  但其实不然
Healthy, even. But they aren't.
这种现象通常只会持续一两天
This usually only lasts for a day or two.
继续
Continue.
然后细胞损伤开始显现
Then the cellular damage begins to manifest.
骨髓坏死  免疫系统失效
The bone marrow dies, the immune system fails,
器官和软组织开始分解
the organs and soft tissue begin to decompose.
动脉和静脉像筛子般破裂
The arteries and veins spill open like sieves,
以至于无法为患者输吗啡
to the point where you can't even administer morphine
来止痛  而且会疼到无法想象
for the pain, which is... unimaginable.
三天到三周后  必死无疑
And then three days to three weeks, you are dead.
这就是那些小伙子的结局
That is what will happen to those boys.
那我们呢
And what about us?
我们...
Well, we've...
我们受到了持续的照射  但剂量不算大
We've gotten a steady dose, but not as much of it.
还不足以杀死细胞
Not strong enough to kill the cells,
不过持续时间足以造成DNA损伤
but consistent enough to damage our DNA.
所以早晚...会得癌症
So, in time... cancer.
或再生障碍性贫血  横竖都是死
Or aplastic anemia. Either way, fatal.
某种角度来说我们还算幸运  瓦列利
In a sense, it would seem we've gotten off easy then, Valery.
我见过他们
I've seen them before.
现在你知道我为什么要出来走走了
Now you know why I wanted to take a walk.
可以肯定我们的工作地点被窃听了
We can presume the work site is bugged.
还有我们的房间  甚至卫生间
And our rooms, even our bathrooms.
他们一直都在这里
They've been here the whole time.
他们当然一直在这里
Of course they've been here the whole time.
但既然我们能直接看到他们
But if we're seeing them out in the open now,
就说明他们想让我们知道
it's because they want us to know.
你看到了吗
You've seen that?
燃料的熔化速度超过了预期
The fuel is melting faster than we expected.
我知道  我有个计划
I know. I have a plan.
希望是热交换器
Heat exchanger, I hope.
对
Yes.
我一直想问你个问题  同志
There's something I've wanted to ask you, comrade,
不过看来你也在思考同一个问题
but I see you're already asking yourself the same question.
它怎么会爆炸呢
Why did it explode?
我把数据算了一遍又一遍
I've worked the numbers over and over,
按照RBMK反应堆可能的最坏条件来假设
presuming the worst possible conditions in an RBMK reactor.
可每次的结论都一样
And I always get the same answer.
结论是
Which is?
它不可能爆炸
It's not possible.
可是...
And yet...
你没办法在这里找到答案
You're not going to solve this here.
在纸上推演没用
Not on paper.
所有在控制室的人
Everyone who was in the control room,
迪亚特洛夫  阿基莫夫  托普特诺夫
Dyatlov, Akimov, Toptunov,
他们都在莫斯科的第六医院
they're all in Moscow, Hospital Number 6.
我们需要查明那晚到底发生了什么
We need to find out exactly what happened that night,
每个时刻  每个决定
moment by moment, decision by decision.
趁他们还活着赶紧去
Go now while they're still alive.
和他们谈谈
Talk to them.
因为如果我们不弄明白这是怎么发生的
Because if we don't find out how this happened,
同样的事还会发生
it will happen again.
还有霍缪克...
And, Khomyuk...
小心点
be careful.
俄罗斯苏维埃共和国  图拉
1986年5月3日
去你妈的
Well, fuck you!
听这个  听这个
Hey, here's one, here's one.
什么东西和房子一样大
What's as big as a house,
每小时要烧20升油
burns 20 liters of fuel every hour,
产生很多的黑烟和噪声
puts out a shit-load of smoke and noise,
却把苹果切成三块
and cuts an apple into three pieces?
答案是本来该把苹果切四块的苏联机器
A Soviet machine made to cut apples into four pieces!
-这里谁负责  -我是工长
- Who's in charge here? - I'm the crew chief.
我是煤炭工业部长谢多夫
I am Shadov, Minister of Coal Industries.
我们认识你
We know who you are.
你有多少人
How many men do you have?
这一班是45人  一共100人
On this shift, 45 here, a hundred in total.
我需要这100人收拾好装备上车
I need all 100 men to gather their equipment and get in the trucks.
是吗  去哪里
Do you? To where?
那是国家机密
That's classified.
那就来吧
Come on, then.
开枪射击吧
Start shooting.
你的子弹不够杀我们所有人的
You haven't got enough bullets for all of us.
尽可能地杀  而剩下来的人
Kill as many as you can, whoever's left,
会把你们几个都揍得满地找牙
they'll beat the living piss out of each of you.
-你不能这么和我们说话  -闭上臭嘴
- You can't talk to us like that! - Shut the fuck up!
这里是图拉  这里是我们的煤矿
This is Tula. This is our mine.
如果不知道原因  我们不会走
We don't leave unless we know why.
你们要去切尔诺贝利
You're going to Chernobyl.
你们知道那边出什么事了吗
Do you know what's happened there?
我们挖煤  不挖尸体
We dig up coal, not bodies.
反应堆燃料即将熔进地下
The reactor fuel is going to sink into the ground
污染从基辅到黑海的水源
and poison the water from Kiev to the Black Sea.
全部水源
All of it.
而且据说是永久性的
Forever, they say.
他们想让你们去阻止这件事的发生
They want you to stop that from happening.
我们要怎么做呢
And how are we supposed to do that?
他们没告诉我  因为我不需要知道这个
They didn't tell me, because I don't need to know.
你们需要知道吗  还是说这就足够了
Do you need to know, or have you heard enough?
你现在这样才像煤炭部长
Now you look like the minister of coal.
瓦西里
Vasya?
别  别  别
No, no, no.
他们说你不能碰我
They told you no touching.
这不安全
It's not safe.
他们不就碰你了
They touch you.
如果他们没事儿  我也一样
If it's safe for them, it's safe for me.
其他人呢
Where are the others?
他们被送去一个特殊病房
They took them to a special room.
但是他们不肯说在哪儿
They won't tell me where.
你能把窗帘拉开吗
Will you open the curtains?
把窗帘拉开
Open the curtains.
拜托  告诉我你看到外面有什么
Please, tell me what you see outside.
告诉我你看到的一切
Tell me everything.
我能看见红场
I can see the Red Square.
还有
And...
克里姆林宫
the Kremlin.
救主塔  列宁陵墓
Spasskaya Tower, the Mausoleum.
你看见圣巴西尔大教堂了
You see St. Basil's?
看见了
Yeah.
看见了  很漂亮
Yes, it's beautiful.
我早跟你说过
I told you.
我说过会带你来看莫斯科  记得吗
I told you I'd show you Moscow, remember?
是啊  我记得
Yeah. Yes.
谢谢你
Thank you.
我才不要吃这个  跟猪食一样
I'm not eating that. It's shit.
换点好的来
Get me something else.
我不是护士  迪亚特洛夫同志
I'm not a nurse, Comrade Dyatlov.
我是个核物理学家
I'm a nuclear physicist.
那么  核物理学家同志
Well, then, Comrade Nuclear Physicist...
除非你正好带着黄油和鱼子酱三明治
unless you happen to have a butter and caviar sandwich on you,
麻烦你滚出我的房间
you can get the fuck out of my room.
怎么
What?
我不擅长这个  鲍里斯
I'm not good at this, Boris.
说谎
The lying.
你和矿工们相处过吗
Have you ever spent time with miners?
没有
No.
我劝你说实话
My advice tell the truth.
他们在黑暗中工作  什么都看得清
These men work in the dark. They see everything.
安德烈·格鲁科夫  工长
Andrei Glukhov, crew chief.
这玩意管用吗
Do these work?
一定程度上  是的
To an extent.
请
Of course.
那要干什么活
So what's the job?
我们要把一个液氮热交换器
We need to install a liquid nitrogen heat exchanger
装在这个混凝土基座下面
underneath this concrete pad.
从建筑内部无法过去
There's no way to approach from the interior of the building,
所以你们得从地下到指定位置
so you have to get at it from underground.
-基座之上是什么  -核反应堆的堆芯
- And what's above the pad? - The core of the nuclear reactor,
而堆芯正在熔毁
which is melting down.
怎么  就像是
What? Like...
大致就是这样
Essentially.
它会不会掉到我们头上
Is it gonna fall on top of us?
如果你们能在六周内完工就不会
Not if you're done within six weeks.
尺寸呢
Dimensions?
从这里开挖
Break ground here,
挖一条150米的隧道到这
dig a tunnel 150 meters to here,
挖出一个30乘30米的空间
excavate a space 30 by 30 meters
来装热交换器
for the heat exchanger.
因为我们需要确保
And because we need to keep
对地面的破坏降到最低
disruption of the ground above to a minimum,
你们不能使用重型机械
you can't use any heavy machinery.
必须要人力完成
It has to be done by hand.
那我需要更多的人手
Then I need more men.
最少四百人
Four hundred at least.
我们需要昼夜赶工
We'll have to work around the clock.
隧道要挖多深  6米吗
How deep do you want this tunnel? Six meters?
-12米  -12米  为什么
- Twelve. - Twelve? Why?
为了保护你们
For your protection.
这个深度能替你们隔绝大部分的辐射
At that depth, you'll be shielded from much of the radiation.
隧道的入口可不在地下12米
The entrance to the tunnel won't be 12 meters below ground.
对
No.
我们现在也不在地下12米
And we're not 12 meters below ground now.
对  我们不在
No. We're not.
在现场有一些设备
We have some equipment here on site.
其它的午夜就到
More will arrive by midnight.
你们早上就可以开工
You can start in the morning.
不  我们现在就开工
No. We start now.
我不希望我的人在这儿多待一秒
I don't want my men here one more second than they need to be.
要是这东西有用  你就戴着了
If these worked, you'd be wearing them.
他们都这样吗
Are they all like that?
他们都这样
They're all like that.
1986年5月6日
爆炸发生9天后
同志们
我们的任务是
保证巷道挖掘每天推进13米
喂
Yes?
-下面最高多少度  -50度
- What's it up to? - 50 degrees.
操
Fuck!
你
Hey you!
-我们需要风扇  -为什么
- We need fans. - For what purpose?
你什么意思  为什么
What do you mean, "for what purpose?"
为了给你挖隧道
To dig your fucking tunnel, that's why.
-谁他妈跟你说话了  -同志
- Who's talking to you? - Comrades.
下面有50度
It's 50 degrees down there.
没有面罩就不能呼吸
We can't breathe without the masks,
戴了面罩喘不上气
we can't breathe with the masks.
里面就是个烤箱  我们需要通风设备
It's like a fucking oven. We need ventilation.
风扇会吹起尘土  尘土会进入你们的肺
Fans will put dust in the air, the dust will go in your lungs.
我的肺已经吸了20年尘土了
I've been breathing dust in my lungs for 20 years.
这种尘土不行  对不起
Not this dust. I'm sorry.
为了你们好  没有风扇
For your own good, no fans.
我是乌拉娜·霍缪克
My name is Ulana Khomyuk.
我是切尔诺贝利委员会的一名物理学家
I'm a nuclear physicist with the Chernobyl Commission.
我想让你告诉我事故当晚
I want you to tell me everything that happened
发生的所有事情
on the night of the accident.
可以吗
Is that all right?
好
Yes.
我愿意说
I want to tell.
好
All right.
你的职位是什么
Your official title was?
我叫列尼德·费罗维奇·托普特诺夫
My name is Leonid Fedorovych Toptunov.
我是切尔诺贝利核电站的
I am the senior reactor control chief engineer
高级反应堆控制总工程师
at Chernobyl Nuclear Power Plant.
高级工程师
Senior engineer?
你多大了
How old are you?
25岁
I'm 25.
柳德  柳德
Lyusya? Lyusya?
我在  我在
Yes, I'm here, I'm here. I'm...
你这段时间一直待在这里吗
Have you been here this whole time?
没人说我该离开
No one said I should leave.
我说了
I did.
我说最多30分钟
Thirty minutes, I said!
那当他痛苦不堪的时候  你去哪儿了
Well, where have you been? When he's in pain?
当他的烂疮黏在病服上的时候
When his sores stick to his gown?
当他一晚拉五次裤子的时候
When he soils himself five times a night?
我一直在照顾他  而你呢
I've been looking after him. Where have you been?
我一直在北翼和西翼
I've been In the north and west wing,
那有数十位和他情况相同的从切尔诺贝利来的病人
where there are dozens of patients from Chernobyl exactly like him.
-你待在这里不安全  -他是我的丈夫
- It isn't safe for you here. - He's my husband.
不再是了
Not anymore.
他已经变得不同了  你明白吗
He's something else now. Do you understand?
他对你来说很危险
He's dangerous to you.
他烧伤了
He's burned.
回家吧
Go home.
求你了
Please.
他时日无多了  我...
It won't take much longer. I, uh...
我不想他孤独地死去
I don't want him to die alone.
待在塑料布外面
Stay on the other side of the plastic.
不然我就让保安把你带走
Or I'll have you removed by security.
-柳德  -我在  亲爱的
- Lyusya? - Yes, my love.
现在是白天吗
Is it day?
不  现在是晚上了
No, it's nighttime now.
我好像做了一个梦
I think I had a dream,
但现在不记得了
it's just gone.
瓦西里
Vasya.
我们要有孩子了
We're going to have a baby.
火灭了
The fire's out.
火灭了  瓦列利
It's out, Valery.
矿工们进展神速
The miners are making incredible progress.
他们说四周就能完成任务
They say the whole job will be finished in four weeks.
四周
Four weeks.
你敢相信吗
Can you believe that?
我知道事情还没结束
I know the job isn't over.
但这是结束的开始
But it's the beginning of the end.
抱歉打扰了  副部长  但是...
I'm sorry to bother you, Deputy Minister, but...
是那些矿工
it is the miners.
怎么了
What?
你不给我们风扇  穿着衣服太热了
You wouldn't give us fans, it's too hot for clothes.
所以我们用老办法挖  我们的父辈就这么挖矿
So we're digging the old way. This is how our fathers mined.
我们还戴着这些该死的帽子
We're still wearing the fucking hats.
你想怎样
What do you want?
你们现在这样得不到防护
You're not as protected now.
你是说穿上那些就能安全了
Are you telling me it will make a difference?
一切结束后
When this is over,
会有人照顾他们吗
will they be looked after?
我不知道
I don't know.
你不知道
You don't know.
功率级从两百兆瓦直接跳到了四百兆瓦
So the power level jumped from 200 to 400 megawatts?
是的
Yes.
非常快
Very fast.
你们为什么没有启动紧急停机
Why didn't you initiate an emergency shutdown?
为什么不按下AZ-5按钮
Why didn't you press the AZ-5 button?
我们按了
We did.
我将数值激增的情况汇报给了阿基莫夫
I reported the increase to Akimov,
他按下了按钮
and he pressed the button.
列尼德  这  这不可能
Leonid, that's... that's not possible.
他按了
He did.
我发誓
I s-swear.
我看着他按下了按钮
I saw him do it.
就在那时发生了爆炸
And that's when it exploded.
什么
What?
-阿基莫夫在哪一间  -27号房
- Which room is Akimov? - Twenty-seven.
我按下了按钮  在爆炸之前
I pressed it... before the explosion.
之前
Before.
但是为什么
But why?
为什么会爆炸
Why would that happen?
我关闭了反应堆  我按下了AZ-5
I shut it down. I pressed AZ-5.
谢谢你  阿基莫夫同志
Thank you, Comrade Akimov.
我的操作没有问题
I did everything right.
出去
Get out.
出去  快出去
Get out. Get out of here.
放开我  放开我
Let me go! Let me go!
住手  住手
Stop it! Stop it!
你让她进屋的吗  进到塑料帘子里  还碰他
You let her in that room? Inside the plastic, touching him?
-你知不知道她怀孕了  -我没有
- Did you know she's pregnant? - It's not true!
-你做了什么  -这是什么地方
- What have you done? - What kind of place is this?
她的保护措施呢
Where is her protection?
-你明不明白现在面临的状况  -我当然明白
- Do you have any idea what you're dealing with? - Of course I do.
-拜托  我没有  -不
- Please, I do not-- - No.
-人们会知道这些事的  -等等
- People are going to hear about this. - Wait.
人们会知道的  你明白我的意思吗
People are going to hear. Do you understand?
所有人都会知道
Everyone is going to hear.
所有人会知道什么
What is everyone gonna hear?
我是切尔诺贝利委员会的官方工作人员
I am with the official Chernobyl Commission,
我受瓦列利·列加索夫的授权调查
and I've been authorized by Valery Legasov.
你可以去确认  我叫乌拉娜
You can check this. My name is Ulana--
我们知道你是谁
We know who you are.
所有人都会知道什么
What is everyone gonna hear?
莫斯科
1986年5月7日
你的笔记带了吗
You have your notes?
带了
Yes.
霍缪克昨晚被逮捕了
Khomyuk was arrested last night.
什么  为什么
What? Why?
我不知道
I don't know.
-是不是...  -当然是了
- Was it--? - Of course it was.
我正在想办法
I'm working on it.
-鲍里斯  -我正在想办法
- Boris-- - I'm working on it.
你还要我做什么
What more do you want from me?
把领带理理
Fix your tie.
他们可以见你们了
They'll see you now.
经过上千次投放
After thousands of sorties,
我们勇敢的直升机组员成功扑灭了大火
our brave helicopter crews successfully extinguished the fire.
矿工们正英勇地工作
The miners are working heroically to ensure
确保堆燃料不会延伸到地下水
that the fuel does not reach the groundwater.
此外
And furthermore,
已经不存在更多爆炸威胁了
there is no longer a threat of additional explosion.
苏联人民在面对挑战时  勇于担当
The Soviet people have faced the challenge and risen to the task,
他们和在座的每一位都值得表彰
and they and everyone in this room are to be commended.
最后  我和列加索夫教授一直在警惕地
Lastly, Professor Legasov and I have been vigilant
保护国家的安全利益
to protect the security interests of the State.
自从事故发生后不久
And since the unfortunate release of information
信息不幸外泄起
directly following the accident,
我们认为没有其他的疏忽
we believe that there has been no further lapse.
佘考夫同志
Comrade Charkov,
我们希望我们达到了克格勃的最高标准
we hope we have lived up to the highest standards of the KGB.
你们达到了
You have.
谢谢
Thank you.
列加索夫教授现在将谈谈剩下的工作
Professor Legasov will now speak about the work that remains.
谢谢
Thank you.
谢比纳副主席给大家带来了好消息
Deputy Chairman Shcherbina has given you the good news,
这确实是好事
and it is good.
迫在眉睫的危险已经过去了
The immediate danger is over.
但恐怕我们要面对一场持久战
Now, I'm afraid, a long war must begin.
大量放射性碎片的
There is an enormous amount of radioactive debris
辐射污染范围高达
and contamination spread out across a zone
大约2600平方公里
of approximately 2600 square kilometers.
因此这整个区域必须全面疏散
This entire region must be completely evacuated.
我们必须去每一个小镇和村子确保疏散的进行
We must go to every town, every village to ensure this.
所有在这片区域内存活的动物
And all animals still surviving within the zone,
无论是家养还是野生的
whether domesticated or wild,
都必须假设它们受到了污染  都必须被消灭
must be presumed contaminated and will have to be destroyed
以防止辐射和疾病的传播
to prevent the spread of radiation and disease.
在切尔诺贝利的邻近周边区域
In the immediate area surrounding Chernobyl,
一砖一树  甚至每寸土地
uh, every rock, every tree, the very ground itself,
都吸收了大量的危险放射性核素
has absorbed a dangerous amount of radionuclides,
如果暴露在外  风和雨会携带辐射散播四处
which will be carried by the wind and the rain if left exposed.
所以我们必须把整片森林夷为平地
So we will have to raze entire forests.
我们必须挖起表层土地
We will have to rip up the top layer of earth
将其埋在地下
and bury it under itself,
这个面积约为100平方公里
approximately, 100 square kilometers.
最后  我们需要
Um, and finally, we will need to
在核电站周围建一个外壳结构
construct a containment structure around the power plant itself,
当然还是极其...
which will, of course, still be extremely...
将会有人死亡
There will be deaths.
你需要多少时间
What amount of time,
需要多少人手
and how many men do you require?
我们预计清理工作需要三年时间
We expect this liquidation effort to take three years
大约需要75万人
and approximately 750,000 men,
包括大量的医生和结构工程师
including a number of doctors and structural engineers.
死亡人数是多少
How many deaths?
数千人
Thousands.
也可能数万人
Perhaps tens of thousands.
立刻开始
Begin at once.
-佘考夫同志  -瓦列利
- Comrade Charkov. - Valery!
什么事  教授
Yes, Professor?
我的同事昨晚被捕了
My associate was arrested last night.
无意冒犯
I mean no disrespect,
但不知你能否告知我原因
but I was wondering if you could tell me why.
我向你保证  我根本不知道你指的是谁
I assure you, I don't know who you're talking about.
她是被克格勃逮捕的
She was arrested by the KGB.
你是克格勃第一副主席
You are the first deputy chairman of the KGB.
没错
I am.
所以现在逮捕人这种小事  我已经不管了
That's why I don't have to bother with arresting people anymore.
但你却百忙之中抽空派人监视我们
But you are bothering with having us followed.
我觉得副主席很忙
I think the deputy chairman is busy.
不  不  这完全可以理解
No, no. It's perfectly understandable.
同志  我知道你听说过一些关于我们的传言
Comrade, I know you've heard the stories about us.
就连我自己听到后  都觉得很震惊
When I hear them, even I am shocked.
但我们并不像人们谣传的那样
But we are not what people say.
没错  是有人在监视你们
Yes, people are following you.
也有人在监视他们
People are following those people.
你看到他们了吗
You see them?
他们在监视我
They follow me.
克格勃就是一个追责圈
The KGB is a circle of accountability.
仅此而已
Nothing more.
你知道我们在这里所做的事
You know the work we're doing here.
-你真的不信任我们吗  -我当然信任
- You really don't trust us? - Of course I do.
但你应该也听过一句俄罗斯谚语
But you know the old Russian proverb:
"没有无条件的信任"
"Trust but verify."
美国人都以为这是罗纳德·里根的名言
And the Americans think that Ronald Reagan thought that up.
你能想象吗
Can you imagine?
很高兴与你交谈
It was very nice speaking with you.
我需要她
I need her.
所以你愿意为她做担保吗
So you will be accountable for her?
那就没问题
Then it's done.
-她叫...  -我知道她是谁
- Her name is--  - I know who she is.
再见  教授
Good day, Professor.
不  这结果出人意料得好
No, that went surprisingly well.
你表现得像个天真的白痴
You came off like a naive idiot.
天真的白痴不是威胁
And naive idiots are not a threat.
等文件手续处理完了  我再过来
I'll come back when the paperwork is complete.
-你没事吧  -他们没有伤害我
- Are you all right? - They didn't hurt me.
他们竟然让个孕妇进屋接触...
They let a pregnant woman into a room with a...
算了  不重要了
It doesn't matter.
他们很愚蠢  我也很愚蠢
They were stupid. I was stupid.
迪亚特洛夫不肯跟我谈
Dyatlov won't talk to me.
阿基莫夫和托普特诺夫都跟我谈了  但...
Akimov, yes, Toptunov, yes, but...
瓦列利
Valery,
阿基莫夫
Akimov...
他的整张脸都被没了
his face was gone.
你想停止调查吗
You want to stop?
我还有这个选择吗
Is that a choice I even have?
你觉得燃料真的会熔穿混凝土层吗
Do you think the fuel will actually melt through the concrete pad?
我不知道  有40%的可能吧
I don't know. A 40% chance maybe.
我说是50%
I said 50.
不管怎样  这些数字都只有一个含义
Either way, the numbers mean the same thing:
"也许"
"Maybe."
也许堆芯会熔穿混凝土进入地下水
Maybe the core will melt through to the groundwater.
也许我派去挖往反应堆地下的矿工
Maybe the miners who I've told to dig under the reactor
能拯救上百万人
will save millions of lives.
也许我只是让他们白白送死
Maybe I'm killing them for nothing.
我不想再这样下去了
I don't want to do this anymore.
我想停下来
I want to stop.
但我做不到
But I can't.
我觉得你也别无选择
I don't think you have a choice any more than I do.
我觉得哪怕面对愚昧
I think, despite the stupidity,
谎言  甚至被捕
the lies, even this...
你也无法不继续
you are compelled.
问题已经出现了  你如果找不到答案
The problem has been assigned, and you will stop at nothing
不会罢休
until you find an answer.
因为你就是这样的人
Because that is who you are.
你是说我是疯子
A lunatic, then.
你是一名科学家
A scientist.
你知道他们当时在做安全测试吗
Did you know that they were running a safety test?
-知道  -不止如此
- Yeah. - There's something else.
阿基莫夫说他们当时关闭了反应堆
Akimov says they shut the reactor down,
托普特诺夫也确认了
and Toptunov confirms it.
-他们按下了AZ-5  -显然还不够快
- They pressed AZ-5. - Apparently not soon enough.
不
No.
他们说阿基莫夫按下了AZ-5
They say Akimov pressed AZ-5,
然后反应堆才爆炸了
and then the reactor exploded.
如果只有一人这么说
If it had been just one of them,
我会觉得可能是记错了  甚至是脑子不清楚
I would have put it under faulty memory or delusion even,
但是他们俩都坚定地表示就是如此
but they both agreed. They were adamant.
同志
Comrade?
-你觉得可能吗  -我觉得这说不通
- Do you think it's possible? - I think it makes no sense.
我觉得如果
I think it's what I would say
我想掩盖我的错误我就会这么说
if I was trying to cover my own mistakes.
但是呢
But?
我相信他们
I believed them.
那你就该查下去
Then you should pursue it.
任何可能性都要追查下去
We have to pursue every possibility,
不管这可能性有多小
no matter how unlikely,
不管到底是谁或者是什么的错
no matter what or who's to blame.
我回医院再问问阿基莫夫和托普特诺夫
I'll go back to the hospital and reinterview Akimov and Toptunov.
如果他们还醒着的话
If they're still awake.
他们死了
They're not.
霍缪克
Khomyuk.